A Guide to the Martin Ashton Hutchinson Papers, 1923-1962
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Martin Ashton Hutchinson Papers 1923-1962
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7736
This collection consists of 756 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were a gift to the library on 16 November 1964 from Mrs. Martin A. Hutchinson, 1625 Westbrook Avenue, Richmond, Virginia, through Joseph H. Harrison, Jr., 11 Ashby Road, Fairfax, Virginia.
Biographical/Historical Information
The son of Daniel Mason Hutchinson and Theresa (Jones) Hutchinson, Martin Ashtin Hutchinson was born in Newport, Giles County, Virginia, on September 13, 1892. Raised on a farm, he attended public schools, and in 1914 he studied at Roanoke National Business College. From 1915-1919 he worked in a law office in Pearisburg and was Deputy Treasurer of Giles County. He served in the army for a seven month period in 1918 and in that same year married Mary Estelle Givens of Craig County by whom he had one daughter, Madge. Hutchinson had helped E. Lee Trinkle in his campaign for the state senate, and Trinkle, later governor, got him a job as journal clerk of the Senate. Hutchinson served in this post from 1920 to 1923. He then served as chief clerk to the secretary of the Commonwealth, 1925-1927. He studied law at night for two years and was admitted to the Virginia Bar on 20 December 1927.
In 1927, Governor Harry F. Byrd appointed him secretary of the Commonwealth; however, Byrd later decided to abolish this office and merge the duties with those of the governor's secretary. Hutchinson opposed this move, not only because he would lose his post, but also because he believed Byrd's plan was undemocratic. Byrd did in fact abolish the job in 1930. Hutchinson devoted himself to the practice of law, mainly tax and corporate cases, in the Richmond firm of Kirsch and Bazile from this time until his death in 1962. He continued to be heavily involved in politics, as he served as secretary of the Democratic State Central Committee from 1925-1939. He became a staunch backer of the progressive governor James Price, and held the post of chairman of the State Compensation Board in Price's administration from 1939-1942. During World War II he was United States Government Appeal Agent, Richmond Local [Draft] Board No. 6.
Through his career, Hutchinson consistently supported the Democratic party on the national level and worked hard for all of the presidential candidates. He greatly admired Franklin D. Roosevelt and criticized Byrd and Carter Glass for their opposition to the New Deal. By the mid-forties, Hutchinson had emerged as one of the leading Democratic liberals who opposed the Byrd "organization" and advocated improved social services and education. In 1946, he challenged Senator Byrd in the Democratic primary. His campaign was handicapped by a lack of money and manpower, however, and he received only 31.6% of the vote. In the wake of his defeat, he and other liberal leaders organized the Committee for Democracy in Virginia to discuss and articulate their political principles.
In 1948 Hutchinson managed and directed the campaign of the Truman-Barkley Straight Ticket Committee, which was believed to have significantly contributed to the Truman victory in Virginia and to have strengthened the liberal cause. Hutchinson actively assisted his friend Francis Pickens Miller in the Democratic gubernatorial primary in 1949 and the senatorial primary of 1952; Miller was defeated on both occasions. In 1950, President Truman nominated Hutchinson for the position of Federal Trade Commissioner, but the nomination was blocked by Senator Byrd for political reasons. By 1954, Hutchinson was suffering from impaired vision and was unable to actively participate in politics during the latter part of his life.
Hutchinson was a member of the Richmond City and American Bar Association, the Scottish Rite Masons of Richmond, and the Virginia Historical Society. He belonged to Centenary Methodist Church where he taught Sunday School. He died of a heart attack on November 27, 1962.
Scope and Content Information
The Martin Ashton Hutchinson collection, ca. 25,000 items (21.7 shelf feet), consists of correspondence, papers and newspaper clippings documenting the political and legal career of this prominent Virginia Democrat, 1923-1962. The principal subject of the correspondence is Democratic party politics, and its theme is Hutchinson's gradual shift from alliance with Harry F. Byrd to leadership of the liberal anti-Byrd faction. The Hutchinson papers would be useful to students of twentieth century Virginia politics and invaluable to those interested in the development of the liberal wing of the state Democratic party. This collection complements the Byrd, Miller, and Whitehead papers in the Manuscripts Department.
In his capacity as state government official, secretary of the Democratic State Central Committee, and party faithful, Hutchinson corresponded with Democratic leaders such as J. M. Hooker, John W. Flannigan, James P. Hart, P. H. Drewry, E. Lee Trinkle, James H. Price, G. Walter Mapp, E. R. Combs, Leonard G. Muse, Claude Pepper, Colgate Darden, and others. The subjects include political strategy, primary and general election campaigns, fund-raising, patronage, and state issues. There are many letters to Hutchinson from persons seeking jobs. Hutchinson corresponded with national Democratic party leaders such as James A. Farley and J. Howard McGrath concerning various presidential campaigns.
In the mid-1930's, Hutchinson expressed his strong support for Franklin D. Roosevelt and the New Deal and in 1945 began to correspond primarily with liberal Democrats who opposed the Byrd organization such as Lloyd M. Robinette, Francis Pickens Miller, Moss Plunkett, Robert Whitehead, and Joseph H. Harrison. There is a great deal of correspondence relating to Hutchinson's unsuccessful bid for the Democratic nomination for senator in 1946, Miller's two unsuccessful primary races, and the formation of the liberal "Committee for Democracy in Virginia" in 1947. Hutchinson corresponded with President Harry S. Truman, his Administrative Assistant Donald S. Dawson, Assistant Attorney General H. Graham Morison, and Senator Paul Douglas concerning his nomination for Federal Trade Commissioner in 1949-1950. There is a little correspondence with J. Lindsay Almond as well. Hutchinson frequently wrote to newspapermen Virginius Dabney, James J. Kilpatrick, and Drew Pearson, discussing political subjects.
The collection includes correspondence pertaining to Hutchinson's law practice, heaviest from 1942-1945, when his political activity was at a relatively low ebb. The only significant family correspondence in the collection is between Hutchinson and his brother Curry P. Hutchinson. These letters discuss not only family matters, but also national, state, and local politics as Curry was extremely active in the Democratic Party in southwest Virginia. Hutchinson also corresponded with his parents Daniel Mason Hutchinson and Theresa (Jones) Hutchinson, his daughter Madge (Mrs. Franklin Marsh), his brother John, and his sister Gertrude. Several folders concerning Hutchinson's participation in Centenary Methodist Church, 1955-1962, complete the correspondence.
In addition to the letters, there are political papers such as speeches, pamphlets, press releases, reports, and campaign account records, and a few business papers. There are also a number of miscellaneous papers such as Sunday School lessons and inspirational quotations. The collection includes many newspaper clippings, mainly relating to politics, and one photograph of Senator Thomas S. Martin. There are seven phonograph recordings of speeches by Hutchinson in his 1946 campaign. Legal case files from Hutchinson's office round out the collection.
Organization
The collection arrived at the library in rough chronological order, and this organization has been retained. The material has been arranged into the following major groups: Political and Business Correspondence; Political and Business Papers, Miscellaneous Papers; Newspaper Clippings; and Legal Case Files. The political, business and family correspondence has all been interfiled and is followed by several folders of correspondence concerning Centenary Methodist Church. The Miscellaneous Papers include the Sunday School lessons and inspirational quotations. All of the material in each of the categories has been arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Political and Business Correspondence: Harry Flood Byrd to MAH 1923 January (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: James B. Botts to MAH 1923 March (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Harry Flood Byrd to MAH 1923 April-May, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Harry Flood Byrd to MAH 1923 August-November, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Harry Flood Byrd to MAH n.d. (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Letters of Recommendation for MAH, etc. 1924 (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Harry Flood Byrd, J. A. Bingham, and MAH 1924 April (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Harry Flood Byrd and George T. Bird to MAH 1924 May (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Harry Flood Byrd to MAH; Pamphlet: "Woodrow Wilson" Memorial Address by E. A. Alderman 1924 August, December (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Harry Flood byrd and B. O. James 1926 May (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Letters of Congratulations and Responses of MAH 1927 April, May (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Condolences on the death of MAH's mother 1928 March (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: E. Lee Trinkle to MAH 1928 April (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH and E. G. Dodson and M. P. Farrier 1929 May (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to Thomas C. Johnson and "To the Democratic Voters of Giles County" 1929 July (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: Political and Business Correspondence: Harry Flood Byrd, and to Editor of Norfolk Ledger-Dispatch1929 (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH and J. M. Hooker and Curry Hutchinson 1930 January (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH and Aubrey G. Weaver 1930 February (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH and R. P. Bruce, etc. 1930 March (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH and Claude F. Beverly, Robert P. Bruce, M. P. Farrier 1930 April (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to C. A. Hardwick, etc. 1930 June (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH and W. S. Barton and C. A. Hardwick 1930 July (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson; MAH to his father 1930 September (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, J. M. Hooker, M. P. Farrier, etc. 1930 October (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to M. P. Farrier, ect. 1930 November (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to J. M. Hooker, etc. 1931 January (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to P. H. Hale, etc. 1931 February (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Harry Flood Byrd, Leon Bazile, etc. 1931 March (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to P. Hale, F. F. Hough, etc. 1931 April (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to P. Hale 1931 May (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH and Leon Bazile, H. F. Byrd, J. B. Haywood 1931 June (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to C. W. Falwell, C. S. Bennett 1931 July (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to Norman R. Hamilton, J. M. Hooker, S. L. Ferguson 1931 August (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to Curry Hutchinson, J. M. Hooker 1931 September (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: S. L. Ferguson to MAH 1931 October (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Chapman S. Hoge, D. R. Hunt, etc. 1931 November (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Whiting C. Faulkner 1931 December (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, P. H. Hale, John W. Flannigan, James P. Hart 1932 January-February (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, James P. Hart, etc. 1932 March (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, James P. Hart, Wilbur C. Hall, Curry Hutchinson 1932 April (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, J. M. Hooker 1932 May (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: T. McCall Frazier, John W. Flannigan, etc. 1932 (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, S. L. Hutchinson, etc. 1932 July (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to Curry Hutchinson, etc. 1932 August (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, James L. Hall 1932 September (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH and P. Hale 1932 October (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, S. L. Ferguson, James Farley, J. L. Hart, etc. 1932 November (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, William M. Fletcher, etc. 1932 December (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1933 January (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, Harry F. Byrd, etc. 1933 February (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: J. M. Hooker, Harry F. Byrd, etc. 1933 March (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: George A. Bowles, Harry Byrd, etc. 1933 April (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: B. A. Banks to Norfolk Ledger-Dispatch[1933 ca. April] (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, L. K. Bussey, etc. 1933 May (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, J. M. Hooker 1933 June (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Harry Flood Byrd, John W. Flannagan, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1933 July (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Harry Flood Byrd, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1933 August (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, E. R. Combs, Curry Hutchinson, Harry Flood Byrd 1933 September (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, James A. Farley 1933 October (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, Harry F. Byrd, etc. 1933 November (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Harry Flood Byrd, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1933 December (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Smith Simpson, etc. 1934 January (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Norman R. Hamilton, etc. 1934 February (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, T. McCall Frazier, John Hutchinson, etc. 1934 March (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, P. H. Drewry, etc. 1934 April (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, A. P. Staples 1934 May (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, etc. 1934 June (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, C. A. Spence, etc. 1934 July (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, Clifton A. Woodrum, etc. 1934 August (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson 1934 September (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: E. Lee Trinkle to E. R. Combs and Peter Saunders, Harry Flood Byrd, Curry Hutchinson, etc. 1934 October (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Harry F. Byrd, James A. Farley, etc. 1934 November (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, J. M. Hooker, Harry Flood Byrd 1934 December (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, H. C. Hypes, etc. 1935 January (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, Curry Hutchinson, John B. Mason, P. H. Drewry, etc. 1935 February (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, C. A. Spence, etc. 1935 March (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to J. M. Hooker and W. H. Schwarzchild, etc. 1935 April (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH and W. H. Schwartzschild, etc. 1935 May (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Harry Flood Byrd, W. H. Schwartzschild, etc. 1935 June (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH. Harry Flood Byrd, John B. Mason 1935 July (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, E. Lee Trinkle, J. M. Trinkle, etc. 1935 August (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, E. Lee Trinkle, H. G. Shirley, S. A. Jessup, etc. 1935 September (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: W. Forbes Morgan, R. L. Ailsworth, Curry Hutchinson, etc. 1935 October (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, Lee Long, Bolling H. Hardy, etc. 1935 November (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, John W. Flannagan, Curry Hutchinson, Clarence K. Reynolds, R. J. Payne 1935 December (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, Curry Hutchinson, etc. 1936 January (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, John Curry, J. H. Britton, etc. 1936 February (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, E. Lee Trinkle, Curry Hutchinson, Pearne Ketron, etc. 1936 March (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Pearne Ketron, Curry Hutchinson, P. H. Drewry, John W. Flannagan, etc. 1936 April (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, M. P. Farrier, G. Walter Mapp, E. Lee Trinkle, Robert Daniel, etc. 1936 May (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, John W. Flannagan, Curry Hutchinson, P. H. Drewry, etc. 1936 June (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, John W. Flannagan, Curry Hutchinson, etc. 1936 July (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, Ivy B. Morgan, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1936 August (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, etc. 1936 September (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Donald T. Stant, Curry Hutchinson, C. S. Carter, B. Forbes Morgan 1936 October (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, W. Forbes Morgan, J. M. Hooker, J. Hume Taylor, W. H. Schwartzschild, etc. 1936 November (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, W. H. Schwartzschild, Lawrence Wood Robert, E. Lee Trinkle, George C. Peery, etc. 1936 December (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, W. H. Schwartzschild, Lawrence Wood Robert, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1937 January (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, M. P. Farrier, etc. 1937 February (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, etc. 1937 March (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Carter Glass, etc. 1937 April (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, J. K. Douglas, etc. 1937 May (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, W. H. Schwartzschild, etc. 1937 June (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1937 July (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker 1937 August (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1937 September (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to J. M. Hooker 1937 October (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker 1937 November (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, E. G. Swem, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1937 December (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1938 January (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, W. H. Schwartzschild, etc. 1938 February (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1938 March (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, E. V. Walker, etc. 1938 April (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Robert W. Daniels, etc. 1938 May (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, R. T. Corbell, etc. 1938 June (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, etc. 1938 July (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, William L. Carleton 1938 August (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Lester J. Cappon, etc. 1938 September (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, John W. Flannagan, etc. 1938 October (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, E. Lee Trinkle, etc. 1938 November (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, etc. 1938 December (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence: American Legion Affairs 1938 (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, G. Walter Mapp, Curry Hutchinson, etc. 1939 January (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, J. M. Hooker, Thomas Davis, etc. 1939 February (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. M. Hooker, John W. Flannagan, etc. 1939 March (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, R. J. Noell, Norman R. Hamilton, etc. 1939 April (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, John W. Flannagan, J. M. Hooker, John M. Hart, etc. 1939 May (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Curry Hutchinson, Oliver A. Quayle 1939 June (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, John W. Flannagan, etc. 1939 July-September, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, E. Lee Trinkle, etc. 1939 October (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, John W. Flannagan, etc. 1939 November (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Alanson Crosby, etc. 1939 December (Box 3)
- Political and Business Correspondence: State of Democratic Opinion in Virginia concerning FDR and the Democratic Convention: MAH, Joseph Leib, David Lawrence 1939-1940 (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, John Flannagan, etc. 1940 January-February, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, James H. Price, etc. 1940 April-June, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH 1940 July (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, James H. Price, etc. 1940 August (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, B. D. Adams, James H. Price, etc. 1940 September (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to Richmond News Leader and Times Dispatch, etc. 1940 October (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, James H. Price, Woody L. Craft, etc. 1940 November (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, J. Franklin, Lloyd Robinette, etc. 1940 December (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Ashton Dovell, James H. Price, etc. 1941 January (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Woody L. Craft, etc. 1941 February (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Lloyd Robinette, etc. 1941 March (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH to Richmond Times Dispatch1941 April (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Vivian L. Page, etc. 1941 May (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Lloyd M. Robinette, etc. 1941 June (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Lloyd Robinette, Claude Pepper, etc. 1941 July (Box 4)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, James H. Price, P. H. Drewry, etc. 1941 August (Box 5)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Lee Long, etc. 1941 September (Box 5)
- Political and Business Correspondence: MAH, Leon Bazile, etc. 1941 October (Box 5)